<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-medved-i2rs-topology-im-00.txt" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="draft-medved-i2rs-topology-im-00.txt">An Information Model for Network Topologies</title>

    <author fullname="Jan Medved" initials="J." surname="Medved">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jmedved@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Nitin Bahadur" initials="N." surname="Bahadur">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>nitinb@juniper.net></email>			
      </address>
    </author>
     <author fullname="Alexander Clemm" initials="A." surname="Clemm">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>alex@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Hariharan Ananthakrishnan" initials="H." surname="Ananthakrishnan">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>hanantha@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="14" month="July" year="2013"/>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines the information model for network topologies.  
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        This document introduces an information model for network topologies.
        The model allows applications to have a holistic view of an entire
        network.  <xref target="I-D.amante-i2rs-topology-use-cases"/> describes
        an entity - the Topology Manager - that would create a cohesive,
        abstracted model of the network and expose it to applications via
        northbound API.
      </t>
      <t>
        The information model can be related to a corresponding data model, for
        example, a data model defined in YANG <xref target="RFC6020"/>, defining
        the actual data that is exchanged across specific interfaces.  On the
        relationship between information and data models, please refer to <xref
        target="RFC3444"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        In order to capture information that is specific to different network
        topology types, this document defines an abstract (basic) topology model
        that can be extended and adapted.  As a result, the information model is
        generic in nature and can be applied to many network topologies.
        Applications can operate on any topology at a generic level where
        specifics of particular topology types are not required, and at a
        topology-specific level when those specifics come into play.  Specific
        topology types that are covered in this document include Layer 3 Unicast
        IGP, IS-IS, and OSPF. We also define the information model for traffic
        engineering (TE) data. Adaptations and extensions to other types of
        topologies (such as Layer 2 topology or OpenFlow topology) are possible,
        using similar model patterns to the ones that are illustrated.
      </t>

      <t>
        This revision of the document focuses on the "live" topology information
        model (<xref target="I-D.amante-i2rs-topology-use-cases"/>, Section
        3.2). The "inventory" and "statistics collection" information models
        will be addressed separately.
      </t>

      <t>
        The information model contains several components:
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Network-Topology">
            contains a generic network topology model.  It defines a network
            topology at its most general level of abstraction. It models aspects
            such as nodes and edges that constitute a topology graph, as well as
            termination points contained in the nodes that actually terminate
            edges of the graph. A network can contain multiple topologies, for
            example topologies at different network layers or overlay
            topologies. The model therefore allows to show relationships between
            topologies, as well as dependencies between nodes and termination
            points across topologies.
          </t>
          <t hangText="L3-Unicast-IGP-Topology">
            applies the general network topology model to Layer 3 Unicast IGP
            topologies.  It extends the general topology with information
            specific to Layer 3 Unicast IGP.  In doing so, it also illustrates
            the extension patterns associated with extending respectively
            extending the general topology model to meet the needs of a specific
            topology.
          </t>
          <t hangText="OSPF-Topology">
            Module "ospf-topology" defines a topology model for OSPF, building
            on and extending the Layer 3 Unicast IGP topology model.  It serves
            as an example of how the general topology model can be refined
            across multiple levels.
          </t>
          <t hangText="IS-IS-Topology">
            defines a topology model for IS-IS, again building on and extending
            the Layer 3 Unicast IGP topology model.
          </t>
          <t hangText="TED">
            defines information kept in the Traffic Engineering Database (TED)
            that is leveraged by IS-IS and OSPF topologies.
          </t>
		</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions and Acronyms">
      <t>
        Data model: An abstract model of a conceptual domain that is intended
        for implementors and contains enough specifics to result in
        interoperable implementations and data representations
      </t>      
      <t>
        Datastore: A conceptual store of instantiated management information,
        with individual data items represented by data nodes which are
        arranged in hierarchical manner.  
      </t>
      <t>
        IGP: Interior Gateway Protocol
      </t>
      <t>
        Information Model: An abstract model of a conceptual domain, independent
        of a specific implementations or data representation
      </t>
      <t>
        IS-IS: Intermediate System to Intermediate System protocol 		
      </t>
      <t>
        LSP: Label Switched Path
      </t>
      <t>
        OSPF: Open Shortest Path First, a link state routing protocol
      </t>
      <t>
        RBNF: Routing Backus-Naur Form
      </t>
      <t>
        URI: Uniform Resource Identifier
      </t>
      <t>
        SRLG: Shared Risk Link Group
      </t>
      <t>
        TED: Traffic Engineering Database
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Network Topology Model Overview">
      <t>
        This section provides an overview of the network topology model.  We
        start with the structure of the foundational model that represents a
        generic topology.  Subsequently, an overview of selected specific
        topologies is given - Layer 3 Unicast IGP, OSPF, and IS-IS,
        respectively. Throughout the document, selected design choices are
        explained and the pattern that should be applied to extend the model to
        new types of topologies is presented.
      </t>
      <t>  
        The network topology model is defined by the following components, whose
        relationship is roughly depicted in the figure below.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="model-structure" align="center" title="Overall model structure">
        <artwork align="left">
           +-----------------------+
           |    Network-Topology   |
           +-----------+-----------+
                       ^
                      /|\
                       | "extends"
           +-----------^-------------+
           |   L3-Unicast-Topology   |
           +--+-------------------+--+
              ^                   ^
             /|\                 /|\
              | "extends"         | "extends"
     +--------^-------+   +-------^-------+    +--------+
     | OSPF-Topology  |   | ISIS-Topology |    |  TED   |
     +--------^-------+   +-------^-------+    +----v---+
              :                   :                 :
              :...................:.................:           
            </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        The Network-Topology component defines the basic network topology
        model. The L3-Unicast-Topology module extends this model with additional
        definitions needed to represent Layer 3 Unicast IGP topologies.  This
        component in turn is extended by OSPF-Topology and ISIS-Topology
        components providing additional definitions for OSPF and IS-IS
        topologies, respectively. The TED component, used by both OSPF-Topology
        and ISIS-Topology components, contains a set of auxiliary definitions
        related to traffic engineering.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Topology Information Model">
      <t> 
        This section specifies the network topology information model in Routing
        Backus-Naur Form (RBNF, <xref target="RFC5511"/>).  It also provides
        diagrams of the main entities that the information model is comprised
        of.
      </t>

      <section title="Base Model: the Network-Topology Component">  
        <t>
          The following diagram contains an informal graphical depiction of the
          main elements of the information model:
        </t>
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                  +----------------+
				  |    topology    |<...
				  +----------------+   :
				    *           *  :   :
				    |           |  :...:
                    |           |
            +--------+        +--------+
        ...>|  node	 |<.......|  link  |<...
        :   +--------+<.......+--------+   :
		:	 :   *                : :  :   :
		:.....	 |                : :  :...:
				 |                : :  
		    +--------+<...........: :
			|   TP   |<.............:
			+--------+          
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          Roughly speaking, the basic information model works as follows: A
          topology contains nodes and links.  Each node in turn contains
          termination points.  A link connects two nodes (a source and a
          destination), terminating on each at a termination point.  Nodes can
          map onto and be supported by other nodes, while links can map onto and
          be supported by other links.  Topologies can map onto other, underlay
          topologies.
        </t>
        <t>
          The information model for the Network-Topology component is more
          formally shown in the following diagram.
        </t>
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  <network-topology> ::= (<topology>...)

  <topology> ::= <TOPOLOGY_IDENTIFIER> 
                 (<node>
                 (<link>...) 
                 [<topology-type>]
                 [<underlay-topologies>]
                 [<topology-extension>]

  <topology-type> ::= (<IGP> [<igp-topology-type>]) | 
                      (<BGP> [<bgp-topology-type>])
  <igp-topology-type> ::= <OSPF> | <ISIS>

  <bgp-topology-type> ::= <>

  <underlay-topologies> ::= (<TOPOLOGY_IDENTIFIER>...)

  <topology-extension> ::= <igp-topology-extension> |
                           <bgp-topology-extension> | 
                           ...

  <node> ::= <NODE_IDENTIFIER> 
             (<termination-point>...) 
             [<supporting-nodes>]
             [<node-extension>]

  <termination-point> ::= <TERMINATION_POINT_IDENTIFIER> 
                          [<supporting-termination-points>]
                          [<igp-termination-point>]

  <supporting-termination-points> ::= 
            (<TERMINATION_POINT_IDENTIFIER>...)

  <supporting-nodes> ::= (<NODE_IDENTIFIER>...)

  <node-extension> ::= <igp-node-extension> |
                       <bgp-node-extension> | 
                       ...
  
  <link> ::= <LINK_IDENTIFIER> 
             <source> 
             <destination> 
             [<supporting-links>]
             [<link-extension> ]

  <source> ::= <termination-point-reference>
  <destination> ::= <termination-point-reference>

  <termination-point-reference> ::= <NODE_IDENTIFIER>
                                    <TERMINATION_POINT_IDENTIFIER>

  <supporting-links> ::= (<LINK_IDENTIFIER>...)

  <link-extension> ::= <igp-link-extension> |
                       <bgp-link-extension> | 
                       ...
           ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The elements of the Network-Topology information model are as
        follows:

        <list style="symbols">
		  <t>
            A network can contain multiple topologies. Each topology is captured
            in its own list element, distinguished via a topology-id.
		  </t>
		  <t>
            A topology has a certain type, such as OSPF or IS-IS. A topology can
            even have multiple types simultaneously.  The type, or types, are
            captured in the list of "topology-type" components.
		  </t>
		  <t>
            A topology can in turn be part of a hierarchy of topologies,
            building on top of other topologies.  Any such topologies are
            captured in list "underlay-topology".
		  </t>
		  <t>
            Furthermore, a topology contains nodes and links, each captured in
            their own list.
		  </t>
		  <t> 
            A node has a node-id.  This distinguishes the node from other nodes
            in the list.  In addition, a node has a list of termination points,
            used to terminate links.  An examples of a termination point might
            be a physical or logical port or, more generally, an interface.
            Also, a node can in turn map onto other nodes in an underlay
            topology.  This is captured in list "supporting-node".
		  </t>
		  <t>
            A link is identified by a link-id, uniquely identifying the link
            within the topology.  Links are point-to-point and unidirectional.
            Accordingly, a link contains a source and a destination. Both source
            and destination reference a corresponding node, as well as a
            termination point on that node.  Analogous to a node, a link can in
            turn map onto other links an underlay topology.  This is captured in
            list "supporting-link".
		  </t>        
          <t>
            The topology, node and link elements can be extended with
            topology-specific components (topology-extensions, node-extension and
            link-extension, respectively). This document defines extensions for
            the L3 unicast topology.
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>
		  The topology model includes links that are point-to-point and
		  unidirectional.  It does not directly support multipoint and
		  bidirectional links.  While this may appear as a limitation, it does
		  keep the model simple, generic, and allows it to very easily be
		  subjected applications that make use of graph algorithms.
		  Bi-directional connections can be represented through pairs of
		  unidirectional links.  By introducing hierarchies of nodes, with nodes
		  at one level mapping onto a set of other nodes at another level, and
		  the introducing new links for nodes at that level, topologies with
		  connections representing non-point-to-point communication patterns can
		  be represented.
        </t>
        <t>
          To minimize assumptions of what a topology might actually represent,
          mappings between topologies, nodes, links, and termination points are
          kept strictly generic.  For example, no assumptions are made whether a
          termination point actually refers to an interface, or whether a node
          refers to a specific "system" or device; the model at this generic
          level makes no provisions for that.  Any greater specifics about
          mappings between upper and lower layers can be captured in extending
          modules.
		  </t>
        <t>
		  Links are terminated by a single termination point, not sets of
		  termination points.  Connections involving multihoming or link
		  aggregation schemes need to be modeled using multiple point-to-point
		  links, then define a link at a higher layer that is supported by those
		  individual links.
        </t>
        <t>
		  In a hierarchy of topologies, there are nodes mapping to nodes, links
		  mapping to links, and termination points mapping to termination
		  points. Some of this information is redundant.  Specifically, with the
		  link-to-links mapping known, and the termination points of each link
		  known, maintaining separate termination point mapping information is
		  not needed but can be derived via transitive closure.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Layer 3 Unicast Topology (IGP) Extensions">
        <section title="The L3-Unicast-Topology Component">
          <t>
            In order to represent a general Layer 3 Unicast IGP topology, the
            basic network topology model needs to be extended.  The
            corresponding extensions are introduced in a component, whose
            structure is informally depicted in the following diagram.
          </t>
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                  +----------------+
				  |    topology    |....
				  +----------------+   :
				    *      *   ^  ^    :
				    |      |  /|\ :....:
        ......      |      |   +------------------+
		:	 :  	|      |      ......           |
        :   +:-------+    +-------:+   :   +-------^--------+
        :..>|  node	 |<...|  link  |<..:   | l3 unicast-IGP |
		 	+--------+<...+--------+       |    topology    |
			     ^             ^           +----------------+
		 	    /|\           /|\              ^         ^
		    	 |             |              /|\       /|\
				 |             |               |         |
		    +----^---+     +---^----+    +-----^--+   +--^-----+   
+------+	| l3 IGP |     | l3 IGP |    |  OSPF  |   | IS-IS  |
|prefix|---*|  node  |     | link   |    |  topo  |   |  topo  |
+------|	+--------+     +--------+    +--------+   +--------+
			 ^      ^        ^     ^
			/|\    /|\      /|\   /|\
     +-------+      |        |     +----------+
	 |              |        |                |
+----^---+    +-----^--+  +--^-----+     +----^---+	
|  OSPF  |    | IS-IS  |  |  OSPF  |     | IS-IS  |
|  node  |    |  node  |  |  link  |     |  link  |
+--------+    +--------+  +--------+     +--------+        
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          Roughly speaking, layer 3 IGP topology refines the generic
          topology, and layer 3 IGP nodes, IGP links, and IGP termination
          points (not depicted) refine the generic nodes, links, and 
          termination points.  In addition, layer 3 IGP nodes can contain
          prefixes.  The pattern recurses with OSPF and IS-IS topologies,
          which are in turn derived from the corresponding layer 3 IGP 
          entities.  
        </t>
        <t>
           A more formal depiction in RBNF format follows below:        
        </t>
          <figure align="center">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  <igp-topology> ::= <TOPOLOGY_NAME>
                     [(<FLAGS>...)]
                     [(<ospf-topology> | <isis-topology>)]

  <igp-node> ::= <NODE_NAME> 
                 (<router-id>...)
                 [(<prefix>...)]
                 [(<FLAGS>...)]
                 [(<isis-node> | <ospf-node>)] 

  <router-id> ::= <ip-address> | <NUMBER>

  <ip-address> ::= (<IPV4><IPV4_ADDRESS>) | (<IPV6><IPV6_ADDRESS>)

  <prefix> ::= <ip-route>
               <METRIC>
               (<FLAGS>...)
               [(<ospf-prefix> | <isis-prefix>)]

  <ip-route> ::= <ip-address>
                 <PREFIX_LENGTH>

  <igp-link> ::= <LINK_NAME>
                 <METRIC>
                 [(<FLAGS>...)]
                 [ (<isis-link> |<ospf-link>) ]

  <igp-termination-point> ::= (<ip-address>...) | <NUMBER>
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The model extends the original network-topology model as follows:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                A new topology type is introduced, igp-topology.  
              </t>
              <t>
                Additional topology attributes are introduced. This allows to
                introduce additional flags in extending modules that are
                associated with specific IGP topologies, without needing to
                revise this component.
              </t>
              <t>
                Additional data objects for nodes are introduced by extending
                the "node" list of the network topology module.  New objects
                include again a set of flags, as well as a list of prefixes.
                Each prefix in turn includes an ip prefix, a metric, and a
                prefix-specific set of flags.
              </t>
              <t>
                Links are extended as well with a set of parameters, allowing to
                associate a link with an IGP name, another set of flags, and a
                link metric.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="The OSPF-Topology Component">
          <t>
            OSPF is the next type of topology represented in the model.  OSPF
            represents a particular type of Layer 3 Unicast IGP.  Accordingly,
            the Layer 3 Unicast IGP topology model needs to be extended.  The
            corresponding extensions are introduced in a separate component
            "ospf-topology", whose structure is depicted in the following
            diagram.  For the most part, this module extends the
            "l3-unicast-igp-topology" component.
          </t>
          <figure align="center">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  <ospf-topology> ::= <AREA_IDENTIFIER>

  <ospf-node> ::= <ospf-router-type> 
                  [<DR_INTERFACE_IDENTIFIER>]
                  [(<MUTLI_TOPOLOGY_IDENTIFIER>...)]
                  [<ospf-node-capabilities>]
                  [<ted-node>]

  <ospf-router-type> ::= <ABR> | <ASBR> | <INTERNAL> | <PSEUDONODE>

  <ospf-node-capabilities> ::= <>

  <ospf-link> ::= [<MULTI_TOPOLOGY_IDENTIFIER>]
                  [<ted-link>]

  <ospf-prefix> ::= [<forwarding-address>]

  <forwarding-address> ::= <IPV4><IPV4_ADDRESS>
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
			The module extends the l3-unicast-igp-topology as follows:
			<list style="symbols">
              <t>
				A new topology type is introduced, ospf-topology-type. 
				</t>
              <t>
				Additional topology attributes are introduced, which extend the
				igp-topology-attributes of the l3-unicast-igp-topology
				component.  The attributes include an OSPF area-id identifying
				the area.
              </t>
              <t>
				Additional data objects for nodes are introduced by extending
				the igp-node-attributes of the l3-unicast-igp-topology
				component.  New objects include router-type, de-interface-id for
				pseudonodes, list of multi-topology-ids, OSPF node capabilities
				and traffic engineering attributes.
              </t>
              <t>
				Links are extended with multi-topology-id and traffic
				engineering link attributes.
              </t>
              <t>
				Prefixes are extended with OSPF specific forwarding address.
              </t>
			</list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="The IS-IS-Topology Component">
          <t>
            IS-IS is another type of Layer 3 Unicast IGP.  Like OSPF topology,
            IS-IS topology is defined in a separate component, "isis-topology",
            which extends "l3-unicast-igp-topology".
          </t>
          <figure align="center">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  <isis-topology> ::= <NET_IDENTIFIER>

  <isis-node> ::= <isis-router-type> <iso>
                  (<NET_IDENTIFIER>...)
                  [(<MULTI_TOPOLOGY_IDENTIFIER>...)]
                  [<ted-node>]

  <iso> ::= <ISO_SYSTEM_ID> <ISO_PSEUDONODE_ID>
  <isis-router-type> ::= <LEVEL_2> | <LEVEL_1> | <LEVEL_2_1>

  <isis-link> ::= [<MULTI_TOPOLOGY_IDENTIFIER>]
                  [<ted-link>]

  <isis-prefix> ::= <>
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
			The module extends the l3-unicast-igp-topology component as follows:
			<list style="symbols">
              <t>
				A new topology type is introduced, "isis-topology-type". 
              </t>
              <t>
				Additional topology attributes are introduced. The attributes
				include an ISIS NET-id identifying the area.
              </t>
              <t>
				Additional data objects for nodes are introduced by extending
				"igp-node-attributes" of the l3-unicast-igp-topology component.
				New objects include router-type, iso-system-id to identify the
				router, list of multi-topology-id, list of NET ids and traffic
				engineering attributes.
              </t>
              <t>
				Links are extended with multi-topology-id and traffic
				engineering link attributes.
              </t>
			</list>
			In addition, the module extends IGP node and link with ISIS attributes.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="The TED (Traffic Engineering Data) Component">
          <t>
            Traffic Engineering Data is required both by OSPF and IS-IS, which
            are defined in separate components.  Information shared by both is
            defined in another component, "TED".  This component defines a set
            of groupings with auxiliary information required and shared by those
            other components.
          </t>
          <figure align="center">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  <ted-node> ::= <te-router-id>
                 <local-address>
                 <pcc-capabilities>

  <te-router-id> ::= [<IPV4><IPV4_ADDRESS>]
                     [<IPV6><IPV6_ADDRESS>]

  <local-address> ::= [((<IPV4><IPV4_ADDRESS>)...)] | 
                      [((<IPV6><IPV6_ADDRESS><PREFIX_OPTION>)...)]

  <pcc-capabilities> ::= <>

  <ted-link> ::= <COLOR>
                 <MAX_LINK_BANDWIDTH>
                 <MAX_RESV_LINK_BANDWIDTH>
                 (<UNRESERVED_BANDWIDTH>...)
                 <TE_DEFAULT_METRIC>
                 [<srlg-attributes>]

  <srlg-attributes> ::= ( <interface-switching-capabilities>...)
                        (<SRLG_VALUE>...)
                        <LINK_PROTECTION_TYPE>

  <interface-switching-capabilities> ::= <switching-capabilities>
                                         <ENCODING>
                                         (<MAX_LSP_BANDWIDTH>...)
                                         [<packet-switch-capable>]
                                         [<tdm-capable>]

  <packet-switch-capable> ::= <MINIMUM_LSP_BANDWIDTH>
                              <INTERFACE_MTU>

  <time-division-switch-capable> ::= <MINIMUM_LSP_BANDWIDTH>
                                     <INDICATION>

  <switching-capabilities> ::= <>
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

            <t>
              This module details traffic-engineering node and
              link attributes:
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>
                  TED node attributes include te-router-id for IPv4 and IPv6,
                  local IPv4 and IPv6 addresses and path computation client
                  capabilities.  The path computation client capabilities in
                  turn include a bit vector for various path computation
                  capabilities.
                </t>
                <t>
                  TED link attributes comprise link color, max-link-bandwidth,
                  max-resv-link-bandwidth, unreserved bandwidth and re-metric.
                  They also include SRLG attributes which contains interface
                  switching capabilities, a list of SRLG values and link
                  protection type.  The interface switching capabilities in turn
                  contains switching capability, encoding, max-lsp-bandwidth and
                  interface switching specific attributes.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Security Considerations">
       <t>
       TBD
       </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
    <t>
    The model presented in this paper was contributed to by more people 
    than can be listed on the author list.  Additional contributors include:
    <list style="symbols" >
		<t>
          Ken Gray, Juniper Networks
		</t>
		<t>
          Tom Nadeau, Juniper Networks
		</t>
		<t>
          Aleksandr Zhdankin, Cisco
		</t>
		<t>
          Tony Tkacik, Cisco
		</t>
		<t>
          Robert Varga, Pantheon Technologies
		</t>
	</list>
	</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
        <t> We wish to acknowledge the helpful contributions, comments, and
        suggestions that were received from many people. We'd also like to thank
        the people that contributed to the topology information model during the
        I2RS Interim meeting in April 2013 - Shane Amante, Andy Bierman, Ed
        Crabbe, Adrian Farrel, and Joel Halpern.
		</t>
    </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
          <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5511"?>
          <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6020"?>
        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">
          <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-amante-i2rs-topology-use-cases-00"?>
          <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3444"?>

		</references>
   </back> 
</rfc>